A Guide to the Merritt T. Cooke Memorial Virginia Print Collection, 1857-1907
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
The Merritt T. Cooke Memorial Virginia Print Collection 1857-1907
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
9408
This collection consists of 80 items.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
This collection was given to the library as a gift from Mrs. Merritt T. Cooke on 1970 January 16.
Scope and Content Information
Include lithographs, engravings, etchings, and watercolors, 1857-1907, of scenic and historic Virginia sites, including several of Virginia churches, Richmond, including one of the burning of the Theatre (1811), White Sulphur Springs (Greenbrier County, W. Va.), White Sulphur Springs (Fauquier County), Natural Bridge, Fayette County, W. Va., Peaks of Otter, and the University of Virginia.
Also contains 42 lithographs from Album of Virginia, published in Richmond in 1858 by Edward Beyer.
Contents List
- Series I: Small Prints (Box 1)
  - Episcopal Church at Richmond, Virginia., engraving 21 x 29 cm (Box 1)
    W. Goodacre, Del. J. Archer Sc.
  - The City of Richmond, from Mayo's Toll House, engraving 18 x 25 cm. (Box 1)
    J. Wood fecit.
  - Episcopal Church at Richmond, Virginia., 21 x 27 cm (Box 1)
    drawn by W. Goodacre, New York; engraved and printed by Fenner Sears & Co. "London Published May 15, 1831 by L. T. Hinton and Sumpkin & Marshall"
  - Falls of the Blackwater., engraving hand tinted 32 x 24 cm (Box 1)
    FWQ Sc. WLS after DHS
  - Falls of the Pedler Virginia, engraving. hand tinted 19 x 13 cm (Box 1)
  - Fortress Monroe and Its Vicinity, engraving, 1862, hand tinted, 22 x 27 cm (Box 1)
    J. Wells, del. R. Hinshelwood, S. C.
  - Great Falls of the Potomac, engraved from a Large Print, 21 x 27 cm. (Box 1)
    By permission of Mr. Nightingale, [?] London: Published by Longman, Hurst, Rees, Orme & Brown, Paternoster Row, May, 1812
  - T.J. Jackson., engraving, 1866, 27 x 17 cm (Box 1)
    Johnson, Fry & Co., Publishers, N. Y., from an original painting by Nast
  - James River, Va., 18 x 23 cm. (Box 1)
    1845 June, by A. Kallner, ink-wash drawing
  - The Lake of the Dismal Swamp, Print. 25 x 38 cm. (Box 1)
    Currier & Ives, colored (crayon?)
  - The Lawn - University of Virginia, etching - 25 x 16 cm. (Box 1)
    by Day Lowry
  - Mill at Marlborough, Maryland., engraving [Stipple?], hand tinted, 22 x 30 cm (Box 1)
    E. Van Blon. J. Hill, Sc.
  - Natural Bridge, Virginia., 29 x 21 cm. (Box 1)
    Drawn by W. Goodacre, N.Y., engraved by T.S. Woodcock, N.Y. Boston: Published by S. Walker
  - The Norfolk Female Institute Polka & Schottisch, 26 x 33 cm. (Box 1)
    Complete sheet music with lithograph hand tinted, on cover. "Lith of Sarony & Major N.Y.
  - Orphan Asylum at Norfolk Virginia., engraving, hand tinted, 13 x 21 cm. (Box 1)
    Eng. D for the Port-Folio Pub. By H. Hall.
  - Portsmouth Ocean House Schottisch., 26 x 33 cm. (Box 1)
    Complete sheet music, composed by Sign. G. George. Published by Geo. Willig. Jr. Baltimore.
  - Richmond, Va. And Its Vicinity., 23 x 29 cm. (Box 1)
    J. Wells, del...AD 1863 by Virtue, Vorston & Co...R. Hinshelwood, S.C.
  - Sir Walter Raleigh ordering the Standard of Queen Elizabeth to be erected on the Coast of Virginia., 29 x 17 cm. (Box 1)
    Engraved for Middleton's Complete System of Geography. Taylor delin. et sculpt.
  - Surrender of Gen. Lee, At Appomattox C. H. Va. April 9th 1865.", 35 x 25 cm. Hand tinted. (Box 1)
    Printed by Currier & Ives, "Entered ...1865 ...
  - University of Virginia, at Charlottesville., engraving, hand tinted, 14 x 22 cm. (Box 1)
  - Valley Falls - Virginia., Print by Currier & Ives, colored (Crayon?) - 25 x 36 cm. (Box 1)
  - View in the Vicinity of Staunton, Virginia., lithograph (?), 18 x 24 cm. (Box 1)
    A. W. Elson & Co., Boston
  - View of Richmond, Virginia., Print - 9 x 12 cm (has been cut down) (Box 1)
    Drawn by C. Fraser. Acquainted by Hill
  - Yorktown, Virginia., engraving, hand tinted - 17 x 22 cm. (Box 1)
- Series II: Edward Beyer Album of Virginia Prints
  - Album of Virginia Illustrated by Ed. Beyer 1858. (Box OS Box M-17)
    Cover to Volume with 4 small oval engravings and 1 larger one; has engravings of George and Martha Washington on back.
  - Blue Sulphur Spring Greenbrier County Va. (Box OS Box M-17)
    has autographs of Edw. Bates, A. Appleton, Wm. Pennington and James D. P. Ogden on back
  - Bullard Rock on the New River Near the River White Sulphur Spr. Giles County, Va., 2 copies (Box OS Box M-17)
    One has engraving of Luther, Melancthon, Pomeranus, and Crucier on back.
  - Burner's White Sulphur Spr. Shenandoah, Co. (Box OS Box M-17)
    has autographs of T.L. Clingman, Johabad (?) Goodwin (Gov., N. H.), John Letcher (Va.), S. A. Douglas, A. Lincoln (facsimile), H. Hamlin (facsimile), and W. A. Gioban (?) on back
  - The Drums. The Tapestry Room, Weyer's Cave. Central R. R. Augusta County, Va. (Box OS Box M-17)
    has autographs of Washington Hunt (Gov., N.Y.), W.A. Buckingham (Gov., Conn.), and Chs. S. Olden (Gov., N.J.) on back
  - Falling Springs Batch County Va. (Box OS Box M-17)
    has engraving of Fredericus Wilhelmus and autographs of James Buchanan, Sam Houston, Jefferson Davis, and J. R. Ingersoll on back.
  - Fauquier White Sulphur Springs Fauquier County Va. (Box OS Box M-17)
    has engraving "Peter the Great Saved by His Mother" on back.
  - Harper's Ferry from Jefferson Rock Jefferson Co. Va. (Box OS Box M-17)
    has autographs of D.S. Duhinson (?), Jethro Arling[?], Jr., H. Winter Davis, and D.D. Barnard on the back.
  - The High Bridge Near Farmville (Box OS Box M-17)
    has engraving of Henry W. Longfellow on back.
  - Hot Springs Bath County, Va. (Box OS Box M-17)
  - James River Canal Near the Mouth of the North River Rockbridge County, Va. (Box OS Box M-17)
    has autographs of W.L. Sharkey, Tho- Bragg (Gov. N.C.), Joseph Lane, W.E. Sinnus (? M.C., Ky.), and Wm. Pennington (M.C.)
  - Kanawha Fall Fayette County, Va. (Box OS Box M-17)
    has engravings of John C. Breckenridge and Joseph Lane, and autographs of J. Tyler, Jere. Clemens, Th. S. Bocock, Edward Everett, and J. P. Benjamin on back.
  - The Little Tunnel Near Shawsville Va. & T. R. R. Montgomery County, Va. (Box OS Box M-17)
    colored. Has engraving by J. Sartain "Richard the Third Endeavoring to Persuade Buckingham..." on the back.
  - Natural Bridge Rockbridge Co. Va. (Box OS Box M-17)
    has autographs of W.C. Rives, Jas. P. Ogden, Geo, Briggs (M.C.), and W.N.H. Smith, and an engraving of Paul Morphy on back.
  - Natural Bridge Rockbridge County, Va. (Box OS Box M-17)
    different view from preceding; has engraving "Louis XVI Threatened by the Mob on Their Visit to the Tuileries, June 20, 1792.
  - "Old Point Comfort" and "Hygeia Hotel", on same print; 2 copies (Box OS Box M-17)
    larger one has engraving of Alexander I of Russia on back.
  - Old Sweet Spr. Monroe County Va. (Box OS Box M-17)
    has engraving of George D.P. Custis [?[ and Alexander von Humbolt with autographs of Ed. Etheridge, Wm. L. Goggin, Thos, H. Clay, and J(?) Holt on back.
  - Red Sulphur Spring Monroe County, Va. (Box OS Box M-17)
    has engraving of Rev. James W. Alexander, D.D. on back.
  - Red Sweet Springs Monroe County Va. (Box OS Box M-17)
    has autographs of I. Towcey, Rev. Thompson, Geo, Briggs, A.B. Moore (Gov., Ala.), and Henry W. Hilliard on back
  - Roanoke Red Sulphur Spr. Roanoke Co. (Box OS Box M-17)
  - Rockbridge Alum Spring Rockbridge County Va. (Box OS Box M-17)
    has facsimile of poem by Thos. Hoors (?)
  - Rockfish Gap and the Mountain House Central R.R. Augusta Co. Va. (Box OS Box M-17)
    has autographs of M. Van Buren, John S. Milburn, W.W. Seaton, B. Magoffin (Gov., Ky.), and John B. Floyd (Gov., Va.) on back
  - The Salt Pond From the Salt Pond Knob Giles County Va. No. 1 (Box OS Box M-17)
    has autographs of Lewis Cass, A.N. Botele (?), J.M. Morehead, and A.J. Hopkins on back.
  - The Salt Pond From the Salt Pond Knob Giles County Va. No. 2 (Box OS Box M-17)
    different view from above.
  - Salt Suphur Spring Monroe County Va. (Box OS Box M-17)
    has engravings of cartoons of Lord North and Mr. Fox, of Mr. Pitt and Mr. Burke, and a portrait engraving of J.A. Quitman on back.
  - Stribling Springs Central R.R. Augusta County Va. (Box OS Box M-17)
    has autographs of W.C. Rives, Thomas G. Turner (Gov., R.I.), B. H. Hill (Ga.), and Wm. L. Dayton on back.
  - U.S. Armory in Harpers Ferry Jefferson County Va. (Box OS Box M-17)
    has facsimile of signed poem by Henry W. Longfellow on back.
  - Viaduct on Cheat River B & O. R. R. Preston County, Va. (Box OS Box M-17)
    has autographs of Winfield Scott, Thos, H. Hicks (Gov., Md.), Jos. Lane, and John W. Ellison on back.
  - View from Gambles Hill Richmond Va. (Box OS Box M-17)
    has signed engraving of Andrew Jackson, and an engraved silhouette of (Jackson) on back.
  - View from Little Sewell Mountain No. 1 Fayette County, Va., 2 copies. (Box OS Box M-17)
    one trimmed more than the other; large print has autographs of Winfield Scott, Balie Peyton, Geo. Evans, and Leslie Conts (?) on the back.
  - View from the Hawks Nest Fayette County Va. (Box OS Box M-17)
    has engraving of bust of Alexander Hamilton with facsimile of signed note by Hamilton
  - View from the Peak of Otter Bedford County, Va. (Box OS Box M-17)
    has poem by Philip Pendleton Cooke on back - facsimile (?)
  - View from the Peak of Otter Redford County, Va. (Box OS Box M-17)
    different view from above; has engraving of W. Maccaulay on back.
  - View of the Peaks of Otter Bedford Cc. (Box OS Box M-17)
    has an engraving of "Galileo" on back
  - Views of Weyer's Cave Augusta Co. Virginia taken from Nature by Ed Beyer 1856" (Box OS Box M-17)
    has four views on front, and autographs of Horace Maynard, Edm. Etheridge, John A. Gilmer, and Jefferson Davis on back.
  - Warm Spring's Bath County Va. (Box OS Box M-17)
    has autographs of Edward Everett, John P. Kennedy, C.C. Clay, Jr., John Young Brown, ?,?, Wm. H. Gist (Gov., S.C.), Hor. Binner and Henry M. Fuller on back.
  - White Sulphur Springs Greenbrier Co. Va. (Box OS Box M-17)
    has autographs of James Buchanan, W. Deurrison (Gov., Ohio), Cl. O'Conor, and Tho. O. Moore (Gov., La.) on back of larger of two copies
  - White Sulphur Springs Montgomery (Box OS Box M-17)
    has photograph (?) of Elisha Kent Kane on back.
  - "Yellow Sulphur Springs Montgomery County Va. (Box OS Box M-17)
    has facsimile of signed poem by J. R. Lowell on back.
- Series III. Large Prints
  - "Birds Eye View of Camp Convalescent near Alexandria, Va., 36 x 50 cm; lithograph [?], hand colored. (Box OS Box M-17)
    at top of print: "Rendezvous of Distribution." "Entered...1864 by Charles Magnus..."
  - Burning of Savannah., colored engraving by Hill. 30 x 38 cm. (Box OS Box M-17)
    Painted by J. Shaw. Published by M. Carey & Son, Philadelphia
  - The Burning of the Theatre in Richmond, Virginia, on the Night of the 26th December 1811, by which Awful Calamity, upwards of seventy five of its most valuable Citizens suddenly lost their lives, and many others, were much injured., engraving [Stipple?] hand tinted. 32 x 40 cm. (Box OS Box M-17)
    Published Feb- 25, 1812, by B. Tanner, No. 74 South St. Philadelphia.
  - Encampment of the Convention Army at Charlotte Ville in Virginia after they had surrendered to the Americans., Engraving. 24 x 35 cm (Box OS Box M-17)
    Published, January 1789 by William Lane, Leadenhall St., London.
  - Hebron Evangelical Church, Madison County, Va., 25 x 32 cm (Box OS Box M-17)
    engraving by Rob. Shaw, H. L. Everett, Publisher.
  - Monument Near Northpoint., engraving colored by hand. (Box OS Box M-17)
    Engraved by J. Hill. Painted by J. Shaw. Published by M. Carey & Son, Philadelphia.
  - Old Blandford Church, Va., 32 x 23 cm. (Box OS Box M-17)
    Engraving by "Rob. Shaw." H. L. Everett, Publisher.
  - St. John's Church, Richmond, Va., engraving. 26 x 32 cm. (Box OS Box M-17)
    H. L. Everett, Publisher.
  - St. Paul's Church, Norfolk, Va., 26 x 32 cm. (Box OS Box M-17)
    engraved by F. Fabar, 1895. Published by H. L. Everett. Insert in borders of [Bishop Beverly D. Tucker].
  - Soldiers Rest, Alexandria, Va. Commanded by Capt. John J. Hoff., lithograph (?), hand colored. 39 x50 cm. (Box OS Box M-17)
    "Entered...1864 by Chas. Magnus..." Published by Chas. Magnus, 12 Frankfort St., N.Y>, & 520 Seventh St., Washington D.C.
  - Spirit Creek; Near Augusta, Georgia., 31 x 39 cm. Hand tinted (Box OS Box M-17)
    engraved by J. Hill. Painted by J. Shaw. Published by Thos. T. Ash, Philadelphia.
  - The University of Virginia, 42 x 76 cm. (Box OS Tray 4)
    Photogravure by, and signed by, Richard Rummell, published by A. W. Elson and Co., Boston. "Copyright 1907 by W. T. Littig & Co., N.Y.
  - University of Virginia, Charlottesville., lithograph from an engraving? 31 x 41 cm (Box OS Box M-17)
  - View of the University of Virginia Charlottesville & Monticello taken from Lewis Mountain., 57 x 75 cm (Box OS Box M-17)
    Published by C. Bohn, Washington, D. C. & Richmond, Va. "Entered...1856...Print in Colors by E. Sachse & Co."
  - Washington's Sepulchre Mount Vernon., 38 x 29 cm. Engraving [?] hand tinted. (Box OS Box M-17)
    Painted by J. Shaw. Engraved by J. Hill. Published by M. Carey & Son, Philadelphia.